Finding Aid for Donald J. Lewis papers, 1961-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donald J. Lewis papers 1961-2007, 1970-1995
Lewis, Donald J. (Donald John), 1926-
1 linear foot
2008017 Aa 2
Donald J. Lewis joined the University of Michigan as a professor of mathematics in 1961. From 1984-1994 he served as the Department of Mathematics chairman. After retiring, Lewis was named professor emeritus by the Board of Regents in June 2000. Materials include: Correspondence, Department of Mathematics records, Professional Activities, Reports and Studies, and Photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Donald J. Lewis in August 2007 (donor no .9932 ).
No further additions to the papers expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Donald J. Lewis, Ph.D., Professor of Mathematics in the College of Literature, Science and the Arts, was born in Adrian, Minnesota on January 25, 1926.
Lewis received his B.S. degree from the College of St. Thomas in 1946, and his M.S. and Ph.D. degrees from the University of Michigan in 1949 and 1950, respectively. From 1950-52 he was an instructor at The Ohio State University, and in 1952-53 he was a National Science Foundation (NSF) fellow at the Institute for Advance Study, Princeton. From 1953-61 he was a faculty member at Notre Dame University. He joined the University of Michigan as an associate professor in 1961 and was promoted to professor in 1963. Lewis served as chair of the Department of Mathematics from 1984-94.
Lewis' research focused on an area of number theory concerned primarily with Diophantine problems and encompassed the theory of algebraic number fields and function fields, and arithmetic geometry. He is the author of 55 research papers and a number of survey papers. He also directed 24 doctoral theses.
From 1995-99 Lewis was based in Washington D.C., as the director of the Division of Mathematical Sciences of the NSF. He received numerous awards including a Distinguished Faculty Achievement Award from the University in 1978, and an Alexander von Humboldt Preis in 1980. He was awarded the American Mathematical Society's Distinguished Public Service Award in 1995 in recognition of his many contributions to mathematics research and education.
Lewis retired from active faculty status on May 31, 2000. In June 2000 the Board of Regents named Donald J. Lewis professor emeritus of mathematics. (Board of Regents Retirement Memoir, June 2000).
The Donald J. Lewis papers consist of correspondence; departmental material; professional studies and reports on mathematic instruction, careers, and women and minorities in math; and photographs, including one of Lewis at the ground breaking of the addition to West Hall (including Patricia Gurin and Homer Neal). The papers consist of five series: Correspondence, Department of Mathematics, Professional Activities, Reports and Studies, and Photographs.
Subjects:
American Mathematical Society.; Lewis, Donald J. (Donald John), 1926-; Mathematics.; National Science Foundation (U.S.); University of Michigan. Dept. of Mathematics.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence 1961-1995
  The Correspondence series (1961-1995, scattered) is divided chronologically among four folders according to decade, and consists of incoming and outgoing correspondence. Correspondents include colleagues from within and outside the University of Michigan, University administrators, Math Department alumni, and donors to the Math Department. Correspondence in the 1984-1989 and 1990-1995 folders is from Lewis' time as chairman of the Math Department.
  - 1961-1962, 1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - 1984-1989 (Box 1)
  - 1990-1995 (Box 1)
- Department of Mathematics 1979-2005
  The Department of Mathematics series (1979-2005, scattered) is divided into three sub-series: Administrative Papers, Committees, and Initiatives/Proposals. The files in each sub-series are organized chronologically. The Administrative sub-series consists of Math Department reviews and reports, Lewis' chairmanship papers, papers from Lewis' time as Development Coordinator for the Math Department, and a lecture on the state of the Math Department written by Lewis. The Committees sub-series documents Lewis involvement in a number of committees within the Math Department. The Initiatives/Proposals sub-series include papers documenting Lewis' work on several grant proposals and program initiatives for the Math Department. Both the Committees sub-series and the Initiatives/Proposals sub-series document Lewis' commitment to improving the quality and variety of mathematics-related programs at the University of Michigan.
  - Administrative Papers
    - Department Reviews/Reports 1979, 2005 (Box 1)
    - Chairmanship Papers 1984-1994 (Box 1)
    - Development Coordinator Papers 1994-1995 (Box 1)
    - Lecture on the Math Department undated (Box 1)
  - Committees
    - Elementary Mathematics Curriculum Committee 1961-1965, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Doctoral Programs 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Programs for Training Mathematics Teachers for Two Year Colleges 1972 (Box 1)
    - Personnel Committee 1994-1995 (Box 1)
  - Initiatives and Proposals
    - Grant Proposal: Summer Research Institute for Young Number Theorists 1972 (Box 1)
    - Actuarial Program Initiative 1992-1995 (Box 1)
    - University of Minnesota/Michigan Curriculum Initiative 1993-1994 (Box 1)
    - Mathematics Computing Labs Equipment Grant Proposal to Hewlett Packard 1994 (Box 1)
    - Math of Finance Degree Program Initiative 1994 (Box 1)
    - Proposal for Undergraduate Concentration in Risk and Finance 1999-2000 (Box 1)
- Professional Activities 1974-1992
  The Professional Activities series (1974-1992, scattered) documents Lewis involvement and leadership in professional organizations outside of the University of Michigan and consists of two sub-series: American Mathematical Society (AMS) and National Science Foundation (NSF). The AMS sub-series consists of papers and correspondence related to Lewis work for the AMS, including his involvement on Committee on Publications, on the Task Force on Unemployment, and in the journal Mathematical Reviews. The NSF sub-series documents Lewis' involvement in the NSF's Alliance for Minority Participation, and a draft of a report and presentation on Natural Science and Engineering in the 1990s.
  - American Mathematical Society (AMS)
    - Mathematical Reviews 1974, 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - AMS Committee on Publications 1976-1977 (Box 1)
    - AMS Task Force on Employment 1991-1992 (Box 1)
  - National Science Foundation
    - NSF Alliance for Minority Participation 1992 (Box 1)
    - Draft of Report and Related Presentation: Natural Science and Engineering in the 1990s, undated (Box 1)
- Reports and Studies 1964-2007
  The Reports and Studies series (1964- 2007, scattered) consists of reports Lewis authored or co-authored during and after his career at the University of Michigan. The reports and studies are organized chronologically. Included are a statement on high school math programs for college bound students, a report on post doctoral education in mathematics, a report on a tour of math programs in Germany, and a review of the math department at Virginia Tech. Also included are materials on the Sloan study, focusing on women in mathematics.
  - Statement on High School Mathematics Program for the College Bound Student 1964 (Box 1)
  - Sloan Study and Related Materials 1986, 1989, 1990-1992 (Box 1)
  - Report on Post Doctoral Education 1991 (Box 1)
  - Report on Germany Tour 1999 (Box 1)
  - Report of the External Review Committee on the Math Department at Virginia Tech 2007 (Box 1)
- Photographs circa 1960s, 1986, and undated
  The Photographs series (ca. 1960s- 1990s, scattered) consist of three photographs. Two photographs are group shots from conferences attended by Lewis and include sheets identifying the conference participants in the photo. The third photograph is a shot of Lewis, Patricia Gurin, and Homer Neal at the ground breaking of the physics addition to what is now West Hall (labeled as East Hall in the photograph).
  - Photographs circa 1960s, 1986, undated (Box 1)
Related Material
For additional material on mathematics at the University of Michigan, researchers are encouraged to consult these additional holdings at the Bentley Historical Library:
University of Michigan, Department of Mathematics records.